A Finding Aid to the William Cushing Loring Papers, 1899-1961, in the Archives of American Art
Archives of American Art
William Cushing Loring papers
1899-1961
Archives of American Art
Loring, William Cushing, 1879-
AAA.loriwill
Archival Resource Key
0.7 Linear feet
The papers of American portrait painter William Cushing Loring (1897-1959) measure 0.7 linear feet and date from 1899-1961. The majority of the collection consists of correspondence, including letters which document Loring's artistic education in Paris and London 1900-1904. Also found within the collection are letters from other Loring family members, printed materials which document Loring's artistic career, and photographs of the artist and his work.
Arrangement
The collection is arranged as three series.
Missing Title
Series 1: Correspondence, 1899-1904 (0.5 linear feet; Box 1-2)
Series 2: Printed Material, circa 1905-1961(4 folders; Box 2)
Series 3: Photographic Material, circa 1905 (4 folders; Box 2, OV 3)
Biographical / Historical
William Cushing Loring (1897-1959) was an American painter and teacher born in Newton Center, MA. He studied at Boston Museum of Fine Arts, Chase's Art School in New York, Academie Colarossi and Academie Delecluse in Paris, and for two years in Holland and London. Loring was best known for his portraiture. He was appointed head of the painting and drawing department at the Rhode Island School of Design in 1905, and taught at La Salle Junior College in Auburn, Massachusetts from 1921 to 1939.
Conditions Governing Access
Use of original papers requires an appointment and is limited to the Archives' Washington, D.C. Research Center. Contact Reference Services for more information.
Existence and Location of Copies
The collection was digitized in its entirety 2016 and is available via the Archives of American Art's website.
Immediate Source of Acquisition
The collection was donated by William Loring Cushing, Jr., son of the artist, in 1985.
Scope and Contents
The William Cushing Loring papers measure 0.7 linear feet and date from 1899-1961. The collection documents Loring's artistic education in Paris and London and his career as an artist and instructor through correspondence, printed materials, and photographs.
Correspondence consists primarily of letters from William Cushing Loring to other Loring family members, including Stanton D. Loring, his father; Mrs. Stanton D. Loring, his mother; Robert Loring, his brother; and Elizabeth and Helen Loring, his sisters. Letters document Loring's life as an artist living abroad in Paris and London. He writes of visits to the studios of John Singer Sargent, Francis David Millet, and Lawrence Alma-Tadema; trips to museums and galleries; excursions to copy paintings in the Louvre and the London National Gallery; evening entertainment; and accounts of daily expenses. Some letters addressed to his parents include illustrations, sketches in ink and graphite, as well as miniature paintings. Letters from Helen Loring and Robert Loring to their parents, as well as unidentified letters, are also present. Envelopes are for the most part matched to letters, but fragment envelopes and letters are integrated within collection.
Printed materials include exhibition catalogs, newspaper obituary clippings for William Cushing Loring, bulletins for Rhode Island School of Design alumni, a holiday card for Loring's studio, and business cards.
Photographic material includes photographs of works of art by William Cushing Loring and photographs of the artist. Photographs of the artist include portraits and photographs of Loring with his family. Included among photographs of works of art are photos by Elmer Chickering.
Sketches; Paintings; Photographs; Illustrated letters; Expatriate painters -- France -- Paris; Art -- Study and teaching -- France -- Paris; Expatriate artists -- England -- London; Art -- Study and teaching -- England -- London; Educators -- United States; Painters -- Massachusetts; Artists' studios -- France; Loring, Robert; Loring, Stanton D.; Loring, Helen; Loring, Elizabeth; Alma-Tadema, Lawrence, Sir, 1836-1912; Millet, Francis Davis, 1846-1912; National Gallery (Great Britain); Musée du Louvre; Sargent, John Singer, 1856-1925; Chickering, Elmer; Rhode Island School of Design
- Correspondence, 1899-1904; Series 1; Archival Resource Key; 0.5 Linear feet Boxes 1-2
  Scope and Contents
  This series, which makes up the bulk of the collection, documents William Cushing Loring's time spent living and studying in Paris and London from 1900-1904. Letters to his parents document Loring's visits to the studios of John Singer Sargent, Francis Davis Millet, and Lawrence Alma-Tadema; painting excursions; painting copies at the Louvre; studies at the Academie Colarossi and the Academie Delecluse; entertainment and nightlife; and daily expenses. Letters addressed to both of his parents and to his mother, Mrs. Stanton D. Loring, include illustrations and sketches in ink and graphite, as well as miniature watercolors. The illustrations often show depictions of Loring's daily life, thumbnail sketches of works in progress, and portraits.
  Letters from Helen Loring and Robert Loring to their parents document their trips abroad to visit their brother in Paris and London. General correspondence addressed to Stanton D. Loring and unidentified correspondence is also included.
  Existence and Location of Copies
  This series has been digitized in its entirety.
  Arrangement
  This series is arranged by correspondent, ordered as letters from William Cushing Loring to his family members, followed by letters written by other family members.
  - Letters to Parents, 1899-1901; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Letters to Parents, 1901; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Letters to Parents, 1902; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Letters to Parents, 1903; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Letters to Parents, 1904; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - Letters to Stanton D. Loring, 1901; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - Letters to Stanton D. Loring, 1902; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - Letters to Stanton D. Loring, 1903; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - Letters to Stanton D. Loring, 1904; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 9)
    Folder includes typed excerpt from diary of Elizabeth Frost "My trip abroad" 1904 found with letters.
  - Letters to Mrs. Stanton D. Loring, 1899-1901; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 10)
  - Letters to Mrs. Stanton D. Loring, 1901; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 11)
  - Letters to Mrs. Stanton D. Loring, 1902; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 12)
  - Letters to Mrs. Stanton D. Loring, 1903; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 13)
  - Letters to Mrs. Stanton D. Loring, 1904; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 14)
  - Letters to Helen Loring and Elizabeth Loring, 1901-1902; Archival Resource Key (Box 2, Folder 1)
  - Letters from Helen Loring to Parents, 1903; Archival Resource Key (Box 2, Folder 2)
  - Letters from Robert Loring to Parents, 1901; Archival Resource Key (Box 2, Folder 3)
  - Letters from Others to Stanton D. Loring, 1900-1902; Archival Resource Key (Box 2, Folder 4)
  - Unidentified Correspondence, 1901-1903; Archival Resource Key (Box 2, Folder 5)
  - Illustrations from Letters, circa 1905; Archival Resource Key (Box 2, Folder 6)
    These illustrations were separated from their associated correspondence before processing.
- Printed Material, circa 1905-1961; Series 2; Archival Resource Key; 4 Folders Box 2
  Found in this series are photocopies of newspaper clippings of obituaries for William Cushing Loring, business cards, a studio card, and originals and photocopies of catalogs from exhibitions at Providence, Rhode Island, and at the Corcoran Gallery. Also included are Rhode Island School of Design alumni bulletins, which show an obituary for Loring, as well as a reproduction of a portrait by Loring.
  Materials are arranged by document type.
  This series has been scanned in its entirety.
  - Business Cards and Holiday Card, circa 1905-circa 1915; Archival Resource Key (Box 2, Folder 7)
  - Exhibition Catalogs, 1916-circa 1940; Archival Resource Key (Box 2, Folder 8)
  - Obituary Clippings, 1959; Archival Resource Key (Box 2, Folder 9)
  - Rhode Island School of Design Alumni Bulletins, 1959-1961; Archival Resource Key (Box 2, Folder 10)
- Photographic Material, circa 1905; Series 3; Archival Resource Key; 4 Folders Box 2, OV 3
  Included in this series are photographs of William Cushing Loring and his work. Photographs of the artist include studio portraits taken in Paris and photographs of Loring with his family. Photographs of works of art include photographs by Elmer Chickering. Photographic types include silver gelatin, copy prints, and an acetate negative.
  Materials are arranged by subject and document type.
  - Photographs of William Cushing Loring, circa 1905; Archival Resource Key (Box 2, Folder 11)
    Oversized materials housed in OV 3.
  - Photographic Negative of William Cushing Loring, circa 1905; Archival Resource Key (Box 2, Folder 12)
    Negative is a duplicate image of photograph of William Cushing Loring from Box 2 folder 11.
  - Photographs of Paintings by the Artist, circa 1905; Archival Resource Key (Box 2, Folder 13)
  - Oversized photographic material scanned with Box 2, Folders 25 and 27, Archival Resource Key (Box OV 3)